Finding Aid to the Victor Robinson Papers, 1898-1947
History of Medicine Division, National Library of Medicine.
Victor Robinson Papers 1898-1947
Robinson, Victor, 1886-1947
2.94 linear feet
MS C 28
History of Medicine Division. National Library of Medicine
Victor Robinson founded the journal Medical life, the first in the English language on the history of medicine, and helped organize the History of Science Society in 1924. The collection contains correspondence, original typescripts, unpublished monographs, articles, notes, and biographical data.
Provenance
Gift from S.R. Shapiro, 1955.
Restrictions
Collection is not restricted. Contact the Reference Staff for information regarding access.
Biographical Note
Victor Robinson (1886-1947), son of a Russian physician, was born in the Ukraine. He studied pharmacy at New York University and the New York College of Pharmacy and law at Columbia University. Robinson received his doctor of medicine degree from the Chicago College of Medicine and Surgery (now Loyola University) in 1917.
He founded Medical life, the first English language journal on the history of medicine, and helped organize the History of Science Society in 1924. In 1932 he photographed and studied archaeological sites of medico-historical interest in Crete, Greece and Italy. In addition to editing Medical life, Robinson also wrote and edited many works on the history of medicine. He was the subject of Victor Robinson, a romantic medical historian (1959) by George Rosen.
Among his own writings are Essay on hasheesh: including observations and experiments (1912, 1925), Pathfinders in medicine (1912,1929), Don Quixote of psychiatry (1919), Pioneers of birth control in England and America (1919), Life of Jacob Henle (1921), Story of medicine (1931), Dr. Jad; the way of life of a physician (1941), Morals in wartime (1943), White Caps; the story of nursing (1946) and Victory over pain; a history of anesthesia (1946). He served as editor for Encyclopedia sexualis; a comprehensive dictionary-encyclopaedia of the sexual sciences (1936), Modern home physician; an encyclopedia of medical knowledge (1938) and New peoples physician; the concise encyclopedia of health (1941).
Collection Summary
The collection contains correspondence, original typescripts, unpublished monographs, articles, notes, and biographical data. Correspondence consists of general correspondence and that pertaining to Encyclopedia sexualis (1933-36). Biographical data relates to contributors to the encyclopedia, and to Chicago otologists. Monographs, articles and drafts include "The price of prudery"; "Riddle of the underworld" (1921) by Ralph Werther; "History of aviation medicine" by Claude Bernard; "Prostitution in France" by Gabriel Giroud; "Sisters in calamity" by Thomas De Quincey; and "Recollections of a prison physician" by Leon Clement Bizard. Contains original typescripts of "Victory over pain: a history of anesthesia"; and "White caps: the story of nursing" (1945). Correspondents are extensive. The Fielding Garrison correspondence (1915-33, ca. 135 items) and drafts of articles by Garrison are arranged separately.
Index Terms
These terms are indexed in the National Library of Medicine's online catalog LocatorPlus. Researchers wishing to find related materials should search the catalog using these terms.
MeSH Subjects
Otolaryngology; Sex; Sexually Transmitted Diseases
Personal Names
Garrison, Fielding H. (Fielding Hudson), 1870-1935; Henle, Jacob, 1809-1885
Series Descriptions
- Series I: Correspondence, 1898-1947
  - A-B, 1910-1946 (Box 1, Folder 1)
  - C-D, 1916-1946 (Box 1, Folder 2)
  - E-F, 1905-1946 (Box 1, Folder 3)
  - G, 1927-1946 (Box 1, Folder 4)
  - H-J, 1913-1944 (Box 1, Folder 5)
  - K, 1904-1947 (Box 1, Folder 6)
  - L, 1912-1946 (Box 1, Folder 7)
  - M, 1909-1945 (Box 1, Folder 8)
  - N-Q, 1913-1945 (Box 1, Folder 9)
  - R, 1911-1948 (Box 1, Folder 10)
  - S, 1912-1946 (Box 1, Folder 11)
  - T-V, 1913-1946 (Box 1, Folder 12)
  - W-Z, 1912-1946 (Box 1, Folder 13)
  - Castiglioni, 1898-1926 (Box 1, Folder 14)
  - Castiglioni festschrift, 1922-1934 (Box 1, Folder 15)
  - Ebstein, 1922-1923 (Box 1, Folder 16)
  - Haberling, 1928-1930 (Box 1, Folder 17)
  - McDonough, 1940-1945 (Box 1, Folder 18)
  - Neuberger, 1921-1934 (Box 1, Folder 19)
  - Sigerist, 1923-1944 (Box 1, Folder 20)
  - Singer, 1921-1934 (Box 1, Folder 21)
  - Sudhoff, 1921-1929 (Box 1, Folder 22)
- Series II: Fielding Garrison Correspondence, 1915-1933
  - 1915-19, 1915-1919 (Box 7, Folder 15)
  - 1920, 1920 (Box 7, Folder 16)
  - January-August, 1921 (Box 7, Folder 17)
  - October-December, 1921 (Box 7, Folder 18)
  - 1922, 1922 (Box 7, Folder 19)
  - 1923-24, 1923-1924 (Box 7, Folder 20)
  - January-June, 1925 (Box 7, Folder 21)
  - July-September, 1925 (Box 7, Folder 22)
  - January-June, 1926 (Box 7, Folder 23)
  - September-November, 1926 (Box 7, Folder 24)
  - 1927, 1927 (Box 7, Folder 25)
  - 1928, 1928 (Box 7, Folder 26)
  - 1929, 1929 (Box 7, Folder 27)
  - 1930, 1930 (Box 7, Folder 28)
  - 1931-33, 1931-1933 (Box 7, Folder 29)
  - Drafts of papers sent to Dr. Robinson by Fielding Garrison, 1919-1921 (Box 7, Folder 30-32)
- Series III: Encyclopedia Sexualis, 1930-1936
  - Biographical data on Encyclopedia Sexualis contributors, 1930-1935 (Box 1, Folder 23)
  - Encyclopedia Sexualis, I-V (Box 3, Folder 20)
  - Encyclopedia Sexualis, VI-X (Box 3, Folder 21)
  - Correspondence, 1933-1936 (Box 2)
    - A, 1933-1935 (Box 2, Folder 1)
    - B, 1933-1935 (Box 2, Folder 2-3)
    - C, 1934-1935 (Box 2, Folder 4)
    - D, 1934-1936 (Box 2, Folder 5-7)
    - E, 1934-1935 (Box 2, Folder 8)
    - F, 1934-1935 (Box 2, Folder 9-10)
    - G, 1934-1936 (Box 2, Folder 11-12)
    - H, 1933-1936 (Box 2, Folder 13-16)
    - I-J, 1934-1936 (Box 2, Folder 17)
    - K, 1934-1936 (Box 2, Folder 18-19)
    - L, 1934-1936 (Box 3, Folder 1-2)
    - M, 1934-1936 (Box 3, Folder 3-5)
    - N-O, 1934-1935 (Box 3, Folder 6)
    - P-Q, 1934-1935 (Box 3, Folder 7-9)
    - R, 1934-1936 (Box 3, Folder 10-11)
    - S, 1933-1936 (Box 3, Folder 12-14)
    - T, 1934-1935 (Box 3, Folder 15)
    - U-V, 1933-1935 (Box 3, Folder 16)
    - W, 1934-1935 (Box 3, Folder 17-18)
    - X-Y-Z, 1934-1935 (Box 3, Folder 19)
- Series IV: A History of Nursing, 1945
  - Introduction, 1945 (Box 4, Folder 1)
  - Chapter I (Box 4, Folder 2)
  - Chapter III (Box 4, Folder 3)
  - Chapter IV (Box 4, Folder 4)
  - Chapter V (Box 4, Folder 5)
  - Chapter VI (Box 4, Folder 6)
  - Chapter VII (Box 4, Folder 7)
  - Chapter VIII (Box 4, Folder 8)
  - Chapter IX (Box 4, Folder 9)
  - Chapter X (Box 4, Folder 10)
  - Chapter XI (Box 4, Folder 11)
  - Chapter XII (Box 4, Folder 12)
  - Chapter XIII (Box 4, Folder 13)
  - Chapter XIV (Box 4, Folder 14)
  - Chapter XV (Box 4, Folder 15)
  - Chapter XVI (Box 4, Folder 16)
  - Chapter XVII (Box 4, Folder 17)
  - Chapter XVIII (Box 4, Folder 18)
- Series V: History of Otology
  - Chapter 1 (Box 5, Folder 1)
  - Chapter 2 (Box 5, Folder 2)
  - Chapter 3 (Box 5, Folder 3)
  - Chapter 4 (Box 5, Folder 4)
  - Chapter 5 (Box 5, Folder 5)
  - Chapter 6 (Box 5, Folder 6)
  - Chapter 7 (Box 5, Folder 7)
  - Chapter 8 (Box 5, Folder 8)
  - Chicago otologists (Box 5, Folder 9)
  - Baltimore otologists (Box 5, Folder 10)
  - Notes-miscellaneous data (Box 5, Folder 11)
  - Notes (Box 5, Folder 12)
  - Notes, 1910-1913 (Box 5, Folder 13)
  - Notes, 1933 (Box 5, Folder 14)
- Series VI: History of Aviation Medicine
  - Chapter I (Box 6, Folder 1)
  - Chapter II (Box 6, Folder 2)
  - Chapter III ( preservation copy) (Box 6, Folder 3-4)
  - Chapter V (Box 6, Folder 5)
  - Chapter VI ( preservation copy) (Box 6, Folder 6-7)
  - Chapter VIII ( preservation copy) (Box 6, Folder 8-9)
  - Chapter IX ( preservation copy) (Box 6, Folder 10-11)
  - Chapter X ( preservation copy) (Box 6, Folder 12-13)
  - Dictionary
    - A-J ( preservation copy) (Box 6, Folder 14-15)
    - K-Z ( preservation copy) (Box 6, Folder 16-17)
    - Notes ( preservation copy) (Box 6, Folder 18-19)
- Series VII: Recollections of a Prison Physician, by Leon Bizard
  - pp. 1-31 ( preservation copy) (Box 6, Folder 26-27)
  - pp. 32-85 ( preservation copy) (Box 6, Folder 28-29)
  - pp. 86-122 (Box 6, Folder 30)
  - pp. 86-122 (preservation copy) (Box 7, Folder 1)
  - pp. 123-170 ( preservation copy) (Box 7, Folder 2-3)
- Series VIII: Victory over Pain
  - Chapter 1 (Box 7, Folder 6)
  - Chapter 2 (Box 7, Folder 7)
  - Chapter 3 (Box 7, Folder 8)
  - Chapter 4 (Box 7, Folder 9)
  - Chapter 5 (Box 7, Folder 10)
  - Chapter 6 (Box 7, Folder 11)
  - Chapter 7 (Box 7, Folder 12)
  - Chapter 8 (Box 7, Folder 13)
  - Chapter 9 (Box 7, Folder 14)
- Series IX: Miscellaneous Articles
  - Notes on syphilis and gonorrhea (Box 5, Folder 15)
  - "Prostitution in France," by Gabriel Giroud (Box 6, Folder 20)
  - "The life of Jacob Henle," pp. 1-18 (Box 6, Folder 21)
  - "The life of Jacob Henle," pp. 19-52 (Box 6, Folder 22)
  - "The price of prudery," Victor Robinson (Box 6, Folder 23)
  - "The riddle of the underworld," Ralph Werther [preservation photocopy], 1921 (Box 6, Folder 24)
  - "The riddle of the underworld," Ralph Werther [includes publisher's contract; ORIGINAL FRAGILE, DO NOT USE], 1921 (Box 6, Folder 25)
  - "Claude Bernard" (Box 7, Folder 4)
  - "Sisters in calamity," by Thomas DeQuincey (Box 7, Folder 5)